{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man received a boost in the polls after he was accused of needing “some kind of Gestapo” to fulfill his policies. This man won an election on the slogan “Let Us Face the Future” and subsequently passed the National Insurance Act on the advice of the Beveridge Report. The British welfare state began under this man, who chartered the creation of the National Health Service. The Potsdam Conference was attended by, for ten points, what Prime Minister who replaced Winston Churchill at the end of World War II?",
      "answer": "Clement Attlee"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who gave the controversial Gazimestan speech, came to power after the “Rallies of Truth,” where his supporters launched the “anti-bureaucratic revolution.” This man’s downfall began when a wheel-loader rammed a government building, giving the Bulldozer Revolution its name. In part because he failed to restrain the actions of commander Ratko Mladic, this man was indicted at the Hague, but he died of heart disease in 2006 before he could be tried. For ten points, name this president of Serbia during the Balkan Wars.",
      "answer": "Slobodan Milosevic"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the Civil War, cannons named for these people were nothing more than disguised logs. Members of this group included abolitionist Anthony Benezet and a “Fighting” major general who lost the Battle of Guilford Courthouse. Nathanael Greene was a member of this religious group, which was founded by George Fox. For ten points, name this pacifist religious group, also called the Society of Friends, whose members included William Penn.",
      "answer": [
        "Quakers",
        "Society of Friends before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "AfterameetingwithHenryMorgenthau,thismanproducedafilmbasedontheideasofairsuperiority purported by Alexander de Seversky. This man, who hired a writing corps known as the “Nine Old Men,” produced a film that includes a dream sequence set in a Nazi factory and salutes to Hitler. Leopold Stokowski conducted the Philadelphia Orchestra for an animated film by, for ten points, what animator and producer of Der Fuehrer’s Face and Fantasia, which star Donald Duck and Mickey Mouse?",
      "answer": "Walt Disney"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler was adopted by the empress Ruqaiya after a soothsayer claimed he would be a great ruler. This man was forced to watch his sons fight for his kingdom at Samurgh after an illness led Dara Shikoh to be named regent. In his final years, this man was confined in the Red Fort, which he had built. This father of Aurangzeb became known for constructing a white mausoleum for his wife, Mumtaz. For ten points, name this Mughal emperor who built the Taj Mahal.",
      "answer": "Shah Jahan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lewis Schwellenbach succeeded this figure, who had an affair with Mary Harriman Rumsey, the founder of the Junior League, until her death. After the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire, this woman served as executive secretary for the New York Committee on Public Safety. Eleanor Roosevelt and this woman oversaw the development of She-She-She Camps during the New Deal. This drafter of the Social Security Act of 1935 was the first woman in the line of presidential succession. For ten points, name this Secretary of Labor under Franklin D. Roosevelt, the first female member of the Cabinet.",
      "answer": "Frances Perkins"
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem set during this war describes how “The larks, still bravely singing, fly / Scarce heard amid the guns below.” In a poem about this war, a man imagines a dying man’s “hanging face, like a devil’s sick of sin,” after describing an “ecstasy of fumbling” after the cries of “Gas! GAS!” A John McCrae poem about this war opens “In Flanders fields the poppies blow.” For ten points, name this war, the subject of Wilfred Owen’s “Dulce et Decorum Est,” which was written while in the hospital suffering from shell shock.",
      "answer": [
        "World War I",
        "the Great War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a book focusing on this event, Rosa Luxembourg described it as a “complete failure.” John Reed’s reporting on this event provided the basis for his book Ten Days that Shook the World. A blank was fired by the Aurora during an attack on the Winter Palace during this event, which occurred months after a Provisional Government was established following a similar event in February. The Bolsheviks planned, for ten points, what autumn 1917 Russian revolution?",
      "answer": [
        "October Revolution",
        "Russian Revolution of 1917 until “John Reed” is read, and prompt after",
        "Bolshevik Revolution until “Bolshevik” is read, and prompt after"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This architect designed a forking glass extension for the Ordrupgaard museum in Denmark and created a pulley system to retract the fabric portion of a roof inspired by the sails of Dhow boats for the Al Janoub Stadium in Qatar. This architect designed the London Aquatics Center in her home nation and was hired to design a Central Bank building in Baghdad, her birth city, shortly before her death in 2016. For ten points, name this Iraqi-British architect, the first woman to win the Royal Gold Medal for architecture and the Pritzker Prize.",
      "answer": "Dame Zaha Mohammad Hadid"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first restrictive regulation on this action was the Page Act, whose intent was reversed sixty years later by the Magnuson Act. This action was carried out through the McCorkell Line during the Irish Potato Famine. A “gentleman’s agreement” under Teddy Roosevelt limited this action from Japan. Many people who performed this action were processed at Angel and Ellis Islands. For ten points, name this action that increases the population of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "immigration to the United States",
        "answers that indicate any country of origin, even though China, Ireland, and/or Japan are the only ones clued"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These people offered a peace deal in which they gave up lands south of the Tugela River to lure in and massacre Piet Retief’s dignitaries. That incident was avenged when these people failed to breach a laager fort set up by Andries Pretorius at the Battle of the Blood River. These people were led by Dingane [din-GAH-nay] and Cetshwayo [key-SHWY-oh], whose armies fought the battles of Rorke’s Drift and Isandlwana against the British. For ten points, name this southern African empire that was led by Shaka.",
        "answer": "amaZulu people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Anglo-Zulu War effectively ended at this July 4, 1879 battle over the Zulu capital city, fought seven months after the British lost at Isandlwana.",
        "answer": "Battle of Ulundi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Peter the Patrician negotiated the end of the Lazic War for this ruler, who had also ended a war with Khosrau I in the Perpetual Peace. The Four Doctors of Bologna revived this man’s law code, the Corpus Juris Civilis. A work by Procopius describes Hypatius’s attempt to rally the Blues and Greens to overthrow this husband of Theodora. The general Belisarius quelled the Nika Revolts for, for ten points, what Byzantine emperor who constructed the Hagia Sophia?",
        "answer": "Justinian I or Justinian the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Procopius described Justinian as possessed by a demon in this highly critical unpublished work, which was discovered in the Vatican in the 17th century.",
        "answer": [
          "Secret History",
          "Historia Arcana",
          "Anekdota"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “a vast majority of mankind is entirely biased by motives of self-interest” while arguing in favor of a minority veto in his posthumous Disquisition on Government. This architect of the Bureau of Indian Affairs declared slavery to be a “positive good” during an 1837 speech to Congress. This man, angered by the 1828 Tariff of Abominations, argued in favor of nullification in an Exposition and Protest. For ten points, name this South Carolina senator and Vice President under Andrew Jackson.",
        "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Calhoun’s Disquisition on Government was highly popular among this group of pro-slavery Southerners. Edmund Ruffin and Robert Barnwell Rhett were among the leaders of this group, which pushed for secession as early as 1850 and which was given its name by critical Northerners.",
        "answer": "Fire-Eaters"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ga¨etan Dugas, a flight attendant who was nicknamed this disease’s Patient O [oh], was erroneously accused of being a North American originator of this disease. Traces of this disease’s type 1 strain have been found in preserved lymph and blood samples from citizens of 1960 L´eopoldville. This disease attacks CD4+ helper T cells, weakening its host’s immune system. For ten points, name this retrovirus that can cause AIDS.",
        "answer": "HIV"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the early 1980s, HIV was known by this name, due to the mistaken understanding that it was endemic to homosexual populations.",
        "answer": "GRID"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a book condemning this event, a thinker stated “Kings will be tyrants by policy when subjects are rebels from principle.” Mary Wollstonecraft responded to that book condemning this event with a book defending republicanism titled A Vindication of the Rights of Men. Edmund Burke argued for gradual change in a book titled Reflections on, for ten points, what event that was triggered by the fall of the Bastille?",
        "answer": "French Revolution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two years after writing A Vindication of the Rights of Men, Wollstonecraft published A Vindication of the Rights of Woman, which attacked this French politician’s attempt to deny women public education. This foreign minister under Napoleon represented France at the Congress of Vienna.",
        "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand-P´erigord, Duke of Talleyrand"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s mayor Ron Norick created a massive municipal improvement project known as MAPS that was funded without debt. The Field of Empty Chairs are part of a memorial in this city that was authorized by Bill Clinton; that memorial commemorates an event that was carried out by a Gulf War veteran who opposed the handling of the Ruby Ridge and Waco standoffs. For ten points, name this city where over 160 people were killed in a 1995 bombing by Timothy McVeigh.",
        "answer": "Oklahoma City"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Timothy McVeigh’s execution in 2001 marked the first execution carried out by the federal government since the decision in this 1972 Supreme Court case, which temporarily ended the death penalty in the US.",
        "answer": "Furman v. Georgia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A temple sculpture at this location consists of a pair of water mirrors intended to view the sky. The Condor Stone is located in a cave in this city where boys underwent a rite of passage during the Royal Feast of the Sun. Advanced irrigation systems in this city rely on water from the Urubamba River. This city was falsely thought to be Vilcabamba Viejo by a Yale lecturer who led an expedition here. Hiram Bingham “re-discovered,” for ten points, what citadel sometimes referred to as the “Lost City of the Incas?”",
        "answer": "Machu Picchu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Machu Picchu is believed to have been built as an estate for this ruler, the ninth Sapa Inca. This grandfather of Huayna Capac ruled until 1471.",
        "answer": "Pachacuti"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A king of this country had a vision of a cross in the sky before winning the Battle of Ourique. The bull Manifestis Probatum recognized Afonso I as the first king of this country. The Battle of Aljubarrota was fought in this country, after which it was ruled by the Aviz dynasty. A prince of this country sponsored voyages to West Africa, sparking the Age of Discovery. For ten points, name this Iberian country that was home to Prince Henry the Navigator.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Portugal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The House of Aviz ruled Portugal for two centuries until the Habsburgs created the Iberian Union; that union lasted until 1640 when this final Portuguese ruling dynasty rose to power.",
        "answer": "House of Braganza"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "19th Century US Legislation",
      "prompt": "For all answers, you need not say “Act,” “Bill,” “Law,” or similar terms. Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ohio Congressman who introduced a massive 1890 Tariff Act, was elected President in 1896, and was shot in 1901.",
          "answer": [
            "William McKinley",
            "McKinley Tariff"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1890 Antitrust Act, named for an Ohio Senator, that was later expanded by the Clayton Act.",
          "answer": "Sherman Antitrust Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 act that offered 160 acres of farmable Western land to citizens willing to improve it.",
          "answer": "Homestead Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1850 act that required Northerners to arrest blacks suspected of having escaped slavery.",
          "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1883 act that reformed civil service by mostly eliminating the spoils system.",
          "answer": "Pendleton Civil Service Reform Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1898 amendment that prevented the US from annexing Cuba during the Spanish-American War.",
          "answer": "Teller Amendment or Teller Resolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "1878 act requiring the Treasury Department to buy quotas of silver and circulate silver dollars.",
          "answer": "Bland-Allison Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "1878 act banning the Army from engaging in domestic law enforcement, given a two-word Latin name.",
          "answer": "Posse Comitatus Act"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Irish Republican Army",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which the IRA believes Ireland should be independent.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland or U.K.",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish political party whose name means “We ourselves” that often associated with the IRA.",
          "answer": "Sinn F´ein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northernmost of the four provinces of Ireland, a Protestant-majority region where loyalists have fought the IRA.",
          "answer": "Ulster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Irish city where the IRA fought the Battle of St. Matthews, and where the Good Friday Agreement was signed.",
          "answer": "Belfast"
        },
        {
          "question": "IRA member who led and died in a 1981 hunger strike in the Maze prison.",
          "answer": "Bobby Gerald Sands"
        },
        {
          "question": "IRA attempt by Patrick Magee to kill Margaret Thatcher.",
          "answer": "Brighton Hotel bombing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Guerrilla warfare strategist for the IRA who, with Arthur Griffith, signed the Anglo-Irish Treaty.",
          "answer": "Michael Collins"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unit, founded by that strategist and commanded by Mick McDonnell, that assassinated members of the Cairo Gang.",
          "answer": [
            "the Squad",
            "the Twelve Apostles"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Activism",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Square in Beijing where democratic activists protested and were crushed by tanks in 1989.",
          "answer": "Tiananmen Square"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home country of Nobel laureate Kim Dae-jung, who was targeted for assassination by dictator Park Chung-hee in 1973.",
          "answer": [
            "South Korea or Republic of Korea",
            "ROK"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Home country of Nobel laureate Mohamed ElBaradei, who briefly became Vice President after a coup against Mohamed Morsi.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Electrician who led the Solidarity trade union against Communist rule and became President of Poland.",
          "answer": "Lech Walesa"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African archbishop who won a Nobel Peace Prize for fighting apartheid.",
          "answer": "Desmond Tutu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where author Ken Saro-Wiwa and the Ogoni Nine were hanged by Sani Abacha’s forces.",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nobel laureate who was imprisoned after signing the Charter 08 manifesto.",
          "answer": "Liu Xiaobo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Venezuelan leader whose namesake doctrine is a refusal to recognize governments that come to power by force.",
          "answer": "Romulo Betancourt"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s losers had their weapons melted down and cast into the three-headed Serpent Column monument. Arimnestus successfully killed the enemy commander with a stone during this battle, and Aristodemus charged the enemy by himself to make up for his absence at (20 pts)",
        "Thermopylae. This battle was fought at the same time as Mycale. Xerxes I returned home prior to this battle, leaving (10 pts)",
        "Mardonius in charge of the loss. For ten points, name this 479 BC battle in which the Greeks ended the Persian invasion."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Plataea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This state was the site of the SS Grandcamp disaster, in which nearly 600 people died after over 4 million pounds of ammonium nitrate exploded in 1947. In April 2013, this state’s town of West was (20 pts)",
        "rocked by another ammonium nitrate explosion. A 2019 chemical plant explosion caused evacuations in this state’s Beaumont-Port Arthur metropolitan area, on the western shores of the (10 pts)",
        "Sabine Lake near the Gulf of Mexico. For ten points, name this state where the booming petrochemical industry fueled the growth of cities like Houston."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ma Rulong led the Hui people during a rebellion against this dynasty before defecting to this dynasty’s side. The lives of Shang Zhixin’s thirty-two brothers were spared in the aftermath of Wu Sangui’s uprising against this dynasty; that incident, the Revolt of the (20 pts)",
        "Three Feudatories, was won by this dynasty’s Green Standard Army, which mobilized under the command of the Kangxi Emperor. This dynasty defeated (10 pts)",
        "Li Zicheng’s forces at the Battle of Shanhai Pass to end the short-lived Shun dynasty. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty founded by descendants of the Jurchen people, called Manchus."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Qing dynasty",
        "Manchus before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This policy was supported by a Payment Law that suspended government subsidies for non-adherents. A disgruntled Edward Kullman was angered into a failed assassination attempt by this policy, which spurred the formation of Ludwig Windthorst’s (20 pts)",
        "Center Party. This policy was strengthened with the passing of Adalbert (10 pts)",
        "Falk’s May Laws, and it led to a ban on Jesuits. For ten points, name this general policy against the Catholic Church that was put forth by Otto von Bismarck."
      ],
      "answer": "Kulturkampf"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Ephesians, one of these objects “of the Spirit” is listed as part of the Armor of God. While praying, Ali was assassinated in 661 with a poisoned one of these weapons. In the Gospels, Jesus stated that he did not come to (20 pts)",
        "“bring peace,” but instead he brought one of these weapons. In a 13th century legend, a hand appears from the waters of a (10 pts)",
        "lake to catch a thrown one of these weapons. For ten points, name this type of weapon whose mythical examples include King Arthur’s Excalibur and one he pulled from a stone."
      ],
      "answer": "swords"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alberto Gentili helped preserve the legacy of this composer by delicately finding private funds to purchase crates of once-lost manuscripts from a religious boarding school in Piedmont and from a descendant of an Austrian ambassador & Genoese count. This composer, the subject of the Turin Collection, composed an opera on the life of (20 pts)",
        "Montezuma and two operas on the story of Orlando Furioso. The Ospedale della Piet`a, an (10 pts)",
        "orphanage and music school, employed this priest and composer of The Contest Between Harmony and Invention, a collection of 12 violin concertoes. For ten points, name this Italian Baroque composer of The Four Seasons."
      ],
      "answer": "Antonio Vivaldi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who defended his actions in a series of letters in the National Intelligencer newspaper, was investigated by the Covode Committee that looked for ways to impeach him. This man sent the army to confront the Mormons in the Utah War, and the (20 pts)",
        "Mountain Meadows massacre occurred during his administration. This president supported the Lecompton Constitution in his attempts to make Kansas a slave state. The end of his tenure was marked by (10 pts)",
        "South Carolina’s secession. For ten points, name this US president who is often criticized for failing to prevent the Civil War and was succeeded by Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "James Buchanan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle proceeded when Forrest Sherman overruled James Doyle on the implementation of Plan 100B. A feint by the HMS Whitesand Bay helped maintain the element of surprise for this battle, which began when one side entered the Flying Fish Channel to strike at (20 pts)",
        "Green, Red, and Blue beaches. Kimpo Airfield was taken as a result of this battle. This battle, codenamed Operation (10 pts)",
        "Chromite, broke the siege of the Pusan Perimeter and led to the recapture of Seoul. Douglas MacArthur masterminded, for ten points, what 1950 amphibious landing that turned the Korean War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Inchon"
    }
  ]
}